(upbeat music)
- Hello English learners,
welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- And today we're gonna be
talking about a very special topic.
- That's right, this topic was actually
suggested by one of our listeners.
- Exactly, so keep those comments coming
because we want to create
lessons that you need, that you want.
- Exactly.
- So what are we talking about today?
- Today's lesson is
about applying for a visa.
- A very, very important topic.
- Yes, and specifically
it's about visa interview.
- Exactly, as you all probably know when
you apply for a visa, especially for the US,
you have an interview, where
you have to answer some questions.
- Yes.
- And that's what we're
gonna be talking about today.
So before we jump into the dialogue,
let's take a look at vocabulary preview.
- Very vocabulary preview.
- Okay, so let's talk about visa.
- Right, a visa, it's not a credit card.
- No, not visa or master card.
- No, so a visa is an official
document that you get in your passport
that allows you to
travel legally to a country.
- Exactly.
So with this document,
you can go into a country.
Okay, so we have different types of visas.
Today we're gonna be
talking about a B2 visa.
- Right, a B2 visa is a tourist visa.
- Tourist visa.
- Yeah.
- This is only for the United States.
Other countries may
have different classifications
for their visas, but B2
is for the United States.
- Right.
- Look, we use a tourist visa when we want
to be a tourist and just travel in the US.
What about a resident visa?
- Well, you can have a
temporary resident visa.
Like for example, an F1.
- Yep.
- An F1 is for foreign exchange students
who go and live in
the States maybe for a
year, or do a MBA for
two years or three years.
So that's an F1 visa.
You can also get a J1 visa, which
is a temporary exchange visitor.
- Okay.
- So it could be to maybe
do some temporary work
for two or three months and
then go back to your country.
- So basically a resident visa
allows you to live in that country.
- Yeah, you can live in that
country legally for a determined time.
Okay, so let's listen to our dialogue.
Where are we gonna be exactly?
- In this dialogue, we're
gonna hear two people.
A visa officer and a person
who's applying for the visa.
Now, the person who's applying
for the visa has an accent, right?
- Yes.
- But this is really good practice
for helping you to understand
people with different accents.
- Exactly.
So let's listen to the
dialogue and then we'll
come back and explain
all the great vocabulary.
(upbeat music)
- So you're applying for a B2 visa.
Where's your final destination?
And what's the purpose of
your trip to United States?
- I'm going to visit my brother.
He's just had a baby.
He lives in Minneapolis.
- And how long do you plan
to remain in the United States?
- I'll be here for
approximately three weeks.
So here's my return ticket
for that 26th of March.
- And who's sponsoring your trip?
- My brother, here.
This is an invitation letter from him.
I will stay with him and
his family in their home.
- All right.
- Tell me about the ties you
have to your home country.
- Well, I own a house, actually I'm
leaving my dog there with my neighbors.
I have a card home.
I know my job.
I'm employed by Toronto as an engineer.
Actually, I only have three weeks vacation.
So I have to go back to
work at the end of March.
- And what evidence do you have
that you are financially independent?
- Well, I do have assets in my country.
Like I said, I own a house and see.
Here's a bank statement showing
my investments and my bank balance.
- I'm sorry, sir.
We cannot grant you a B-2 visa this time.
Instead, you are granted a resident visa.
Congratulations.
You are the millionth
person to apply for visa.
You win.
Congratulations.
- All right.
What a lucky guy he applied for a tourist
visa and now he's getting a resident visa.
- Yeah, that's great.
But does this really happen?
- No.
No, that would never happen at a consulate.
- Okay, well, we can dream
that this might happen for us.
- Yeah, exactly.
All right, let's take a look at the
words in language takeaway today.
- Language takeaway.
- All right, on language
takeaway, we have sponsoring.
- Sponsoring.
- So Erica, what does it
mean to sponsor somebody?
- When you sponsor somebody for a visa,
you take care of them and make
sure they have enough money.
- Okay.
- So you are the one who's
responsible for all of their
expenses and making sure
they just have enough money.
- Okay.
So for example, when
I was 16, I made a trip
to another country and my
parents were my sponsors.
- So they took
responsibility for your money.
- Exactly.
Okay, let's look at our
next word, invitation letter.
- Invitation letter.
- Now this is a really important
part for a visa application.
- Yes, very important.
- What is an invitation letter?
- Well, an invitation
letter is a formal letter
that a friend or a relative
or maybe a business
writes to ask you to
come to their country.
- Exactly.
So you're being invited for a
specific purpose to the United States.
- Yeah, and you have to give
this letter to the visa officer.
- Okay, invitation letter.
- Our next word, ties.
- Ties.
- Looks exactly like tie like
the one you wear in your suit.
- Not quite the same though.
All right, so what are ties?
- The ties you have to your country
are the things that keep
you attached to your country.
- Okay.
- That make sure that you
will return to your country.
- Okay, so what are some examples of ties?
- Like maybe a house or a wife or a child
or maybe some money in your bank account?
- Okay.
- Or a job even.
- Okay, okay, perfect.
- Yeah, a good way to think of this is
imagine like a rope that's attached to you
and tying you to your country, to
your house, to your job, to your kids.
- Okay, so you can't run away.
- Exactly.
- Okay, okay, that was
clear, but let's listen
to some more examples
of how we would use ties.
- Example one.
- I sold my house and
closed my bank account.
I don't have any more
ties to my home country.
- Example two.
- Alvin enjoyed being single.
He wasn't ready for
the ties of family life.
- Example three.
- Diplomatic relations have improved
and the ties between the
two countries are stronger.
- All right, it's clear now.
Let's look at our next word,
financially independent.
- Financially independent.
- So that means that you don't need anyone.
- That you have enough money.
- You have enough money for yourself.
- Right, so you don't
have to ask your parents
to pay for your ticket or
pay for your food or whatever.
- Okay, and our last
word for today, assets.
- Assets.
- Okay, so your assets
are kind of like your ties.
- Right, there are things
of value that you own.
Things that are expensive that
you own in your home country.
- So it would be a house, a car.
- Yep, maybe stocks, or investments.
- Okay, so all of those
things are your assets.
Okay, so we've seen a lot of great words
and I think it's time for us to
listen to our dialogue again.
We're gonna slow it down for you.
- Yeah, this will help you
understand it a little bit better.
(upbeat music)
- So you're applying for a B2 visa.
Where is your final destination
and what is the purpose of
your trip to the United States?
- I'm going to visit my brother.
He's just had a baby.
He lives in Minneapolis.
- And how long do you plan
to remain in the United States?
- I'll be here for
approximately three weeks.
- See, here's my return
ticket for the 26th of March.
- And who is sponsoring your trip?
- My brother, here.
This is an invitation letter from him.
I'll stay with him and
his family in their home.
- All right, tell me about the ties
you have to your home country.
- Well, I own a house.
Actually, I'm living my dog
there with my neighbors.
I have a card home, I know my job.
I'm employed by Toronto as an engineer.
Actually, I only have three weeks vacation.
So I have to go back to
work at the end of March.
- And what evidence do you have
that you are financially independent?
- Well, I do have assets in my country.
Like I said, I own a house
and see, here's a bank
statement showing my
investments and my bank balance.
- I'm sorry, sir.
We cannot grant you a B2 visa this time.
Instead, you are granted a resident visa.
Congratulations.
You are the millionth
person to apply for a visa.
You win.
Congratulations.
- Yay.
(upbeat music)
- Okay, today we're
not gonna do a regular
toolkit, like Fluency
Builder, putting it together.
- No, we're gonna do something
a little bit different today.
- We're gonna talk about the questions
you will probably be asked
at an interview for a US visa.
- Yes.
- And they use full
language that you can
use to answer these
questions in a good way.
Okay, so let's take a
look at our first question.
- Where is your final destination?
And what is the purpose of
your trip to the United States?
- Where is your final destination?
And what is the purpose of
your trip to the United States?
- So this is probably gonna be the first
question the interview is gonna ask you.
- Yeah, so Marco, I know you have
a lot of experience with US visas.
How should we answer this question?
- Well, it depends on
what you're doing, right?
- Right.
- So if you're a tourist,
you would say I'm
going on vacation to
New York or anywhere.
Also, if you're visiting a family member
like in our dialogue, you would say,
oh, I'm gonna visit my sister
or my brother or my cousin.
If you're applying for a business visa,
then you would say, oh, I'm
gonna visit a company or et cetera.
- Right.
- So you just have to say
why you are going to the state.
- Now, is it important
to be really specific?
- Yeah, the more specific
you are, it's probably better.
So if you can name the state and the
city where you're going, it's much better.
- Okay, all right, well, let's
listen to our next question.
- How long do you plan to
remain in the United States?
How long do you plan to
- Okay, so this is a really important
question also because in your application,
you have to put how long
you plan to stay in the US.
- Right.
- It's a pretty straightforward answer.
You know, two months,
one month, three weeks.
- Right, but you just have to
make sure that your answer matches.
- What's written in your application?
- Yeah. - Exactly.
Okay, now let's take a
look at our last question.
- Tell me about the ties you
have to your home country.
- Well, I think this is maybe the most
important question that the last ski, right?
- Yeah, this is the most
important question.
This is what the interviewer
is most interested in.
- Okay, so why is he interested in this?
- Because he has to
be sure that you will not
become an illegal immigrant
to the United States.
- So that you will return
to your home country?
- Exactly, he or she has to be convinced
that you're gonna return
to your home country.
- So how can you convince him?
- Basically, by demonstrating your ties,
so showing the things that will
pull you back to your home country.
- So if you take
documents to support this
bank statements, maybe
a copy of your mortgage.
- Yep, like maybe your wedding certificate?
- Wedding certificate, I don't know, even
a letter from your office from your job.
- So the shows that you
have to return to your work?
- The more things you bring the better,
even though the interviewer
might not ask for the documents.
- Okay, it's better to be safe, right?
- Exactly.
- So come with a huge file, things.
I've had friends who've
arrived to the embassy
with a huge file of documents
and weren't asked to show
any of the documents, but other
interviewers will maybe ask for it.
Okay, so now let's listen
to the dialogue again.
- And you'll hear how our
traveler answers these questions.
(upbeat music)
- So you're applying for a B2
visa, where's your final destination
and what's the purpose of
your trip to the United States?
- I'm going to visit my brother.
He's just had a baby.
He lives in Minneapolis.
- And how long do you plan
to remain in the United States?
- I'll be here for
approximately three weeks.
So here's my return ticket
for that 26th of March.
And who's sponsoring your trip?
- My brother, here.
This is an invitation letter from him.
I will stay with him and
his family in their home.
- All right.
Tell me about the ties you
have to your home country?
- Well, I own a house.
Actually, I'm leaving my
dog there with my neighbors.
I have a cat home.
I know my job.
I'm employed by Toronto as an engineer.
Actually, I only have
three weeks of vacation,
so I have to go back to
work at the end of March.
- And what evidence do you have
that you are financially independent?
- Well, I do have assets in my country.
Like I said, I own a house and see.
Here's a bank statement
showing my investments.
And my bank balance.
- I'm sorry, sir.
We cannot grant you a B2 visa this time.
Instead, you are granted a resident visa.
Congratulations.
You are the millionth
person to apply for visa.
You win.
Congratulations.
- Well, I hope this was a useful
lesson for all of our listeners,
because I'm sure that
in one point or another,
in the future, you're
going to apply for a visa.
So now you know all the language
that you need to more or less answer
all these questions that
you're going to be asked.
- Yes.
And Marco, I'm sure that people have
already applied for visas for the US, right?
- Probably, yeah.
- And I want to hear
from our users any stories
that they have about
applying for a visa.
- Yeah, that would be great.
I know that I have some stories
to share on the comments board.
And we want to hear your questions
and comments and any suggestions.
- So visit our website
at www.englishpod.
com and Marco and I will be there to
respond to you and answer your questions.
Well, everyone, thanks for listening.
And until next time, bye.
(upbeat music)